Joseph Kleszczynski Collection CPAA 02.14
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Joseph Kleszczynski Collection
1966-2000
CPAA 02.14
Connecticut Polish American Archives
0.5 Linear feet
Joseph Kleszczynski was born in 1928 in Poland. He completed his primary education in Poland. Still a teenager, he joined the Polish Underground Army in 1943. With advancement of the Soviet Army in the beginning of 1945, he decided to flee Poland and eventually joined the Polish Army in Italy under General Wladyslaw Anders. With his army unit he left for Great Britain, where he attended college. In 1952, he immigrated to the United States, completed his education and worked for the U.S. Postal Service. He was and still is very active in many Polish American organizations and teaches Polish language courses in the town of West Hartford, CT. In 2011, he was one of the honorees during the Immigrant Day at the state Capitol in Hartford.
Kleszczynski, Joseph
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Kleszczynski was born September 4, 1928 in Jakubowice, Poland. He attended grade school and high school in Krakow, Poland and in 1943 joined the Polish Underground Army and graduated a cadet officer from infantry officer’s school. After the Soviet Red Army advanced from the east in 1945 he was forced to flee the country because the Underground Army was dissolved and many members were imprisoned by the NKVD (the Soviet secret police). He fled through Czechoslovakia to the American zone of occupied Germany. Later he joined the Polish Army in Italy in the 2nd Polish Corps of General Anders Army under British Command. Several months later he left for England together with his unit and attended a junior college. In the spring of 1946, he was honorably discharged from the Polish Army. He attended an agricultural school, graduating in 1949 in Glasgow, Scotland. In 1951, he received a scholarship from the Free Europe Organization in New York to attend Cornell University College of Agriculture in Ithica, NY. He also attended the University of Hartford to receive a real estate license. In 1954, he married Mary C. Wilusz and they had four children. He worked in various companies and in 1966 received a federal position with the U.S. Postal Service. He participated in several Polish American support organizations such as The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs (STUDIUM), the Polish American Congress (PAC), the Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations, the Free Eagle Organization, and Foundation in Support of Local Democracy. Mr. Kleszczynski teaches Polish language at the West Hartford Continuing Education. In 2011, the Connecticut Immigrant and Refugee Coalition (CIRC) selected him as one of the honorees for the immigrant Day at the State Capitol. He is still active in organizations such as the Polish American Foundation of Connecticut, Inc where he serves on the Board of Advisors and a constable for the town of West Hartford, CT.
STUDIUM, or The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs, established in 1975, was an organization active in the U.S. and Canada. Their main goal was to distribute information about current status of the political and economic situation in Poland and among Polonia to prominent politicians, intellectuals and English language newspapers. STUDIUM was dedicated to the goal of Poland's independence.
The Polish American Congress (PAC), a nationwide umbrella organization, was established in 1944 in Buffalo, NY. PAC has many state divisions and PAC of Connecticut is one of a very strong and active division. Some of their work included settling refugees and finding work, events such as Pulaski Day Parade, and working with media and government to help Polish Americans. Their main goal was to advocate for Poland's independence from a communist government. PAC, with its state divisions, was responsible for a successful action to bring Poland to NATO's membership. The organization is still active today and provides assistance to Poland and Polish Americans.
Based out of Hartford, CT and established in 1967, The Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations participated in protests and letter writing campaigns to the United Nations, the U.S. Congress, and other government agencies. Twenty-six countries were represented in the committee.
The Free Eagles Organization focused on forming a union, called Federation by the group, between eastern European countries to create peace and order in Europe and to free the eastern European countries from the oppression of communist governments.
Formed in 1989, The Foundation in Support of Local Democracy is a non profit, independent group. They promote the idea of civil self-governance by supporting the activity of local authorities and non-governmental organizations. In Poland especially, they have provided training courses about democratic practices in order to reform Poland’s local authority and democracy.
Scope and Contents note
Papers related to activities of STUDIUM, Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations, and PAC Connecticut district, from 1966 until 2000.
North American Study Center for Polish Affairs; Polish American Congress. Connecticut Division -- Periodicals; Polish Americans -- Connecticut; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Politics and government; Polish Americans -- Correspondence; Polish Americans -- Political activity
- The North American Study Center for Polish American Affairs (STUDIUM), 1975-1993; This series contains related papers for STUDIUM. (Box 1)
  - STUDIUM The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs– memos, notes, announcements., 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - STUDIUM – Announcements, press releases, agendas, budgets., 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - STUDIUM – Various membership lists and related information (Polish too), 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - STUDIUM – List of names for possible membership with annotations., 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - STUDIUM – General infromation about meetings and conventions of Studium., 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - STUDIUM – Strategic plan for 1990-1993. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “Polish Trade Unions and the Right to Strike” position paper prepared by Studium., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - STUDIUM- Komunikaty [newsletter]., 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - STUDIUM- Komitet Organizacyjny [Organizing committee]., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - STUDIUM- By-laws and the Articles of Incorporation-October 19, 1982-March 30, 1984 (drafts), 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - STUDIUM- Articles, clippings, essays., 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - STUDIUM- Program and ideological declaration, June 1975; By-laws 1984, 1975; 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - STUDIUM - Correspondence., 1975-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Foundation in Support of Local Democracy- Related material, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations, 1968-1991; Papers related to the Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations and the Free Eagle Organization. (Box 1)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations - meeting announcements and minutes., 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations- Correspondence, 1967-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations- Correspondence, 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations- Clippings, articles, general information., 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations- Proclamations, press releases., 1967-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations- "Polish-Ukrainian Relations" by J. Iranek-Osmecki; Czechoslovak-Polish Confederation by Joseph Kalvoda, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Connecticut Committee for Captive Nations - photographs, stationary., 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Free Eagles Organization, Inc. (Organizacja Wolnych Orlow) - periodical publication To Freedom (Ku Wolnosci)., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Free Eagle Organization - newsletter, flyers, correspondence., 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Polish American Congress, 1966-2001; This series contains papers related to the Polish American Congress. and Jozef Kleszczynski's biographical information. (Box 2)
  - Polish American Congress Connecticut District- Meeting agendas and treasurer reports., 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, memos, reports., 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, memos, reports, agendas., 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, announcements, Polish American newsletters (Including CCSU)., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, reports, memos., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, memos, membership info., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - PAC CT District– Credit Union Initiative: correspondence, agenda, committee., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - PAC CT District- Announcements., 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - PAC CT District- Correspondence, appeals,notes., 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - PAC CT District- Committee of Polish Affairs., 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - PAC CT District- Manifesto to commamorate Poland's Millenium of Christianity., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - PAC National– 10th National Convention, Report from the Chicago office and Report of the Veterans Committee by Z.A. Konikowski., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - PAC Illinois Division Summary of Activities; Western New York Division Report., 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - PAC Michigan Division– Bi-Annual Report., 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - PAC National 9th National Convention, Detroit, MI, October 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - PAC National – Memorandum on German revisionism, Feb. 1969; German revisionism in the United States, organizations and partners, 1971, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - PAC National– Correspondence., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - PAC National and CT District – various brochures, membership forms, newsletter (1984), and surveys., 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - PAC CT District - Polish American Agenda and related material., 2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NSZZ Solidarnosc, Staszow Region 1980-1982, memoirs by Jozef Malobecki. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Brochures and flyers from various organizations., 1998-2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Jozef Kleszczynski - biographical information (Box 2, Folder 22)